A Guide to the Jones family papers, 1775-1995
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Jones family papers, 1775-1995
The Library of Virginia
44050
5 cu. ft. and 10 boxes
Jones family
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Robert and Jane Bennett, Davis, California.
Biographical Information
The Jones family resided in Botetourt County and Lexington, Virginia. The Joneses' extended family line included members of the Scott, Moorman, Houston, Alexander, and Stuart families.
Scope and Content
Jones family papers, 1775-1995, consisting of Bible records, biographies, books, business records, clippings, cloth, correspondence, currency and bonds, genealogical notes and charts, land records, magazines, photographs, portraits, and silhouettes concerning the Jones family of Botetourt County and Lexington, Virginia. Papers concern the genealogy of the Jones and related families.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I: Genealogy.
Series II: Correspondence, 1847-1949.
Series III: Papers, 1835-1938.
Series IV: Land Records, 1783-1890.
Series V: Currency and bonds, 1775-1777, 1861-1865.
Series VI: Photographs.
Series VII: Miscellaneous papers and envelopes.
Series VIII: Newspaper clippings.
Series IX: Magazines.
Series X: Books.
Series XI: Material.
Contents List
- Series I: Genealogy., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 1-2)
  Genealogy contains Bible records, biographies, clippings, correspondence, DAR applications, genealogical notes and charts, memorials, obituaries, photographs, and programs concerning the Jones, Scott, and Houston families of Botetourt County and Lexington, Virginia, as well as other localities in Virginia and West Virginia. Also includes brief research notes on the Alexander, Ashton, Blair, Lewis, Ronald, Slaughter, Smith, Stuart, Todd, and Wigginton families. Also contains handwritten and typed transcripts of the will of Gabriel Jones (ca. 1737-1777) and handwritten transcripts of the will of Marion Stuart Alexander Jones (1828-1912), as well as correspondence concerning Marion Jones' will. Also contains copy of a deed for Julia M. Mayo's life interest in a farm in Botetourt County. Also, a sketchbook containing quotes and spurious letter by Publius Lentulus describing Jesus.
  - Jones family (folder 1 of 4). (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Jones family (folder 2 of 4). (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Jones family (folder 3 of 4). (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Jones family (folder 4 of 4). (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Descendants of Gabriel Jones of Essex and Culpeper Counties, Virginia. (Box 1)
  - Jones/Scott family (folder 1 of 3). (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Jones/Scott family (folder 2 of 3). (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Jones/Scott family (folder 3 of 3). (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Scott family. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Houston family (folder 1 of 3). (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Houston family (folder 2 of 3). (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Houston family (folder 3 of 3). (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Name research. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Wills. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1847-1949., Extent: 1 box. (Box 2)
  Correspondence, 1847-1949, contains letters concerning news about the Alexander, Jones, and related families concerning family news and events. Much of the correspondence is to Marion Stuart Alexander Jones from her step-mother Judith Blackburn, her sister Mariette Alexander McGuire, her step-son Edward Valentine Jones, and her step-daughter Susan Archer Jones. Letters also discuss the Civil War in King George County, Virginia; the settlement of the estate of Judith Blackburn Alexander; and Edward Valentine Jones' education and ministry. Also includes copy of letter from President James A. Garfield (1831-1881) to his mother and a letter from the United States Battleship Maine Salvage Company endeavoring to raise funds to raise the U.S.S. Maine from the Havana, Cuba, harbor.
  - Correspondence, 1847-1860. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1862-1865. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1866-1869. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1870-1899. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1901-1912. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1945-1949. (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Series III: Papers, 1835-1938., Extent: 1 box. (Box 2)
  Papers, 1835-1938, contain the papers of John Wigginton Jones (1807-1894) consisting of deeds, receipts, surveys, judicial records, accounts, promissory notes, articles of agreement, wills, ads, tax records, correspondence, bonds, and appraisements concerning the Jones and Finney foundry, real property in Botetourt County and Genesee County, Michigan, Jones' estate, Jacob Finney's (d. 1859) will, and other matters relating to J. W. Jones; Moorman family papers, 1835-1888, consisting of correspondence and papers containing family news, news about a missionary school in Greece, bonds, trip to London, England, and J. J. Moorman's career as a doctor at the Warm Sulphur Springs in West Virginia; Edward Herndon Scott's (1839-1872) journal detailing his service in Missouri during the Civil War; and Scott's Civil War papers including military passes, receipts, military parole, and list of the battles of the Stonewall Brigade, also an 1866 account and 1867 tax receipt for Scott.
  - John Wigginton Jones papers, 1839-1938. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Moorman family papers, 1835-1888 and no date. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Edward Herndon Scott journal, 1861-1862, (typescript). (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Edward Herndon Scott journal, 1861-1862, (original). (Box 10)
  - Edward Herndon Scott Civil War papers, 1863-1865. (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Series IV: Land Records, 1783-1890., Extent: 1 box. (Box 2)
  Land Records, 1783-1890, contain surveys, 1794-1805 and no date, and deeds, 1783-1890, for land in Botetourt County. Also, correspondence, 1869-1876, concerning the sale of property.
  - Deeds, 1783-1890. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Surveys, 1794-1805 and no date. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1869-1876. (Box 2, Folder 17)
- V: Currency and bonds, 1775-1777 and 1861-1865., Extent: 1 box. (Box 2)
  Currency and Bonds, 1775-1777 and 1861-1865, contain notes issued by Virginia during the American Revolution and notes issued by various banks in Virginia and by the Confederate government during the Civil War. Also contain bonds issued by the Confederate government.
  - Currency and bonds, 1775-1777 and 1861-1865. (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Series VI: Photographs., Extent: 4 boxes. (Box 3-4, 7-8)
  Photographs of the Jones family; Eddie Scott (Mary Edward Herndon Scott Jones [1872-1932]); family and friends of Eddie Scott; the Moorman family; Civil War generals and politicians and Charles Carter Randolph; and Robert E. Lee (1807-1870). Also includes silhouettes of members of the Jones family and a copy of a portrait of George Mason (1725-1792).
  - Jones family. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Eddie Scott (Mary Edward Herndon Scott) (folder 1 of 3). (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Eddie Scott (folder 2 of 3). (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Eddie Scott (folder 3 of 3). (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Friends and family of Eddie Scott (folder 1 of 4). (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Friends and family of Eddie Scott (folder 2 of 4). (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Friends and family of Eddie Scott (folder 3 of 4). (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Friends and family of Eddie Scott (folder 4 of 4). (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Moorman family. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Civil War politicians and generals; Charles Carter Randolph. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Robert E. Lee. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Photograph of Eddie Scott and cross medal. (Box 7)
  - Photograph of Rutherford Houston and son. (Box 7)
  - Photograph of Edward Herndon Scott (probable). (Box 7)
  - Photograph of [-] Houston. (Box 7)
  - Photographs of an unidentified woman. (Box 7)
  - Photograph of an unidentified man. (Box 7)
  - Advertisement for Myron Shew, daguerrotype dealer, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. (Box 7)
  - Silhouette of John Wigginton Jones. (Box 7)
  - Silhouette of Mary Elizabeth Valentine Jones. (Box 7)
  - Silhouettes of an unidentified man and woman. (Box 7)
  - Portrait of George Mason. (Box 8)
  - Empty album cover. (Box 8)
- Series VII: Miscellaneous papers and envelopes., Extent: 1 box. (Box 4)
  Miscellaneous papers and envelopes contain list of births and deaths for slaves owned by the Joneses; poems; teacher certificate from King George County; last words of unidentified individual; recipes for whitewash and boot repair and cures for illnesses including dropsy; table of box sizes; description of a coat-of-arms; pictures of buildings; memorandum and account book; list of Virginia county formation; sign language alphabet card; and invitation to a picnic held by Mountain Home school. Also contain envelopes.
  - Miscellaneous papers. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Envelopes. (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Series VIII: Newspaper clippings., Extent: 1 box. (Box 4)
  Newspaper clippings contain clippings concerning the Jones family, genealogy, history, the Civil War, and other topics. Also include poems.
  - Newspapers. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper clippings. (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Series IX: Magazines, 1862-1898., Extent: 1 box. (Box 4)
  Magazines contain issues of the following magazines: The Household Companion (18 January 1897); The Ladies' Home Journal ad (1892); The Peterson Magazine (January 1898); Southern Literary Messenger (November 1862-February 1864) run and some issues incomplete; and The Virginia Seminiary Magazine (January 1892).
  - The Household Companion, 18 January 1897. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - The Ladies' Home Journal ad, 1892. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - The Peterson Magazine, January 1898. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Southern Literary Messenger (incomplete), November-December 1862. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Southern Literary Messenger February 1863. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Southern Literary Messenger (incomplete), September 1863. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Southern Literary Messenger February 1864. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - The Virginia Seminary Magazine January 1892. (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Series X: Books., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 5-6)
  Books containing volumes acquired by members of the Jones family including the Bible and the Book of Common Prayer, as well as books on religion and theology, poetry, novels, history, and genealogy.
  - The Houston Family in Virginia by Leslie Lyle Campbell. (Box 5)
  - The Bible. (Box 5)
  - The New Testament (includes Jones family births and deaths). (Box 5)
  - Practical Truths by Archibald Alexander. (Box 5)
  - Sketches of Virginia Historical adn Biographical by William Henry Foote. (Box 5)
  - The Book of Common Prayer. (Box 5)
  - Historic Culpeper. (Box 5)
  - In Old Narragansett by Alice Morse Earle. (Box 5)
  - The Taming of the Shrew by William Shakespeare. (Box 5)
  - Daily Food for Christians. (Box 5)
  - The Book of Common Prayer. (Box 5)
  - Letters on the Improvement of the Mind by Mrs. Chapone; a Father's Legacy to his Daughters by Dr. Gregory; a Mother's Advice to her Absent Daughters by Lady Pennington. (Box 5)
  - Blank note pad. (Box 5)
  - The Irish Race in America by Michael O'Meagher Condon. (Box 6)
  - the Apostolic Origin of the Episcopacy Asserted by John Bowden. (Box 6)
  - Reliques of Ancient English Poetry by Thomas Percy. (Box 6)
  - The Lady of the Lake by Sir Walter Scott. (Box 6)
  - The Works of Laurence Sterne volume II. (Box 6)
  - The Bible. (Box 6)
  - The Book of Common Prayer. (Box 6)
  - Our Home Beyond the Tide by Ellen E. Miles. (Box 6)
  - Golden Thoughts from the Psalms. (Box 6)
- Series XI: Material., Extent: 1 box. (Box 9)
  Material contains lace, including gloves, and a blanket.
  - Lace. (Box 9)
  - A blanket (or cloth). (Box 9)